Jiakun Yan

☑ jiakuny3@illinois.edu • ❷ jiakunyan.github.io

Research Interests

My research interest lies in **parallel computing**. Currently, I am interested in co-designing high-level task-based programming models and low-level communication systems to better utilize modern parallel architectures and improve the performance, scalability, and programmability of modern parallel applications.

Education

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Illinois, USA

Aug. 2020 -

- o Computer Science PhD student, advised by Marc Snir .
- o Pursue research in Parallel Computing.
- o GPA: 4.0/4.0 | Relevant Courses: CS523 Advanced Operating System (ongoing), CS533 Parallel Computer Architecture, CS526 Advance Compiler Construction, CS483 Applied Parallel Programming, CS450 Numerical Analysis.

Shanghai Jiao Tong University

Shanghai, China

o Bachelor's Degree of Engineering, Dept. of Computer Science.

- Sep. 2016 Jun. 2020
- o Zhiyuan Honors Program of Engineering (an elite program for top 5% talented students)
- o GPA: 91.88/100 | Ranking: 4th/151.

University of California, Berkeley

California, USA

o Exchange student, Berkeley Global Access Discover Program, GPA: 4.0/4.0.

Jan. 2019 - May 2019

Experience

Programming Systems and Applications Research Group

NVIDIA Research

Research Intern, advised by Michael Bauer and Michael Garland

May. 2022 - Aug. 2022

o Realm Collective: design and implement collective communication operations in Realm.

PASSION Lab

Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory

Research Assistant, advised by Aydın Buluç and Katherine Yelick

Aug. 2019 - Jan. 2020

- o Asynchronous RPC Library (ARL): a high-throughput RPC system with node-level aggregation and single-node work-stealing.
- o RDMA vs. RPC for Implementing Distributed Data Structures

Publication

o Benjamin Brock, Yuxin Chen, **Jiakun Yan**, John Owens, Aydın Buluç, and Katherine Yelick. "RDMA vs. RPC for Implementing Distributed Data Structures", Workshop on Irregular Applications: Architectures and Algorithms (IA3), 2019.

Project

HPX over LCI UIUC

Advised by Prof. Marc Snir

Aug. 2021 - Present

- o The High Performance ParalleX (HPX) is a runtime system known for its support for the asynchronous task programming model. Currently, HPX uses MPI as its major communication backend. In this project, we would like to add an LCI parcelport for HPX and compare the new HPX/LCI system with the original HPX/MPI system to investigate: (a) how efficiently the current LCI can interact with HPX. (b) where LCI can further improve to better support the communication requirement of asynchronous task frameworks.
- o To date, an initial implementation of the LCI parcelport is completed. It has been shipped with HPX 1.8.0. We are working on the performance evaluation.

Lightweight Communication Interface

UIUC

Advised by Prof. Marc Snir

Aug. 2020 - Present

- o The Lightweight Communication Interface (LCI) is designed to be a low-level communication library used by high-level libraries and frameworks. It aims to support irregular and asynchronous applications such as graph analysis, sparse linear algebra, and task-based runtime on modern parallel architectures. Major features include (a) support for more communication primitives such as two-sided send/recv and one-sided remote put (b) better multi-threaded performance (c) explicit user control of communication resource (d) flexible signaling mechanisms such as synchronizer, completion queue, and active message handler.
- o I am one of the major developers of LCI. Main contributions include developing the Libfabric backend of LCI and designing/implementing LCI v1.7 along with a parameterized testing framework. I am working on evaluating the multi-threaded performance of LCI and exploring ways, such as utilizing multiple hardware contexts, to improve its multi-threaded performance.

TaskFlow: Task-based Runtime on Distributed-memory System

UIUC

Advised by Prof. Josep Torrellas and Marc Snir, CS533 course project

Jan. 2021 - May 2021

- o TaskFlow is a simple but efficient task-based runtime for distributed-memory systems. It adopts the PTG-based task programming model that enables reduced time/memory overhead and fine-grained synchronization. It executes tasks according to an explicit task dependency graph and uses active messages to proactively signal remote tasks.
- o We implement TaskFlow based on Argobots and MPI. We perform a collection of micro-benchmarks and mini-applications to evaluate the performance of its various configurations and compare it with two established PTG-based task systems, TaskTorrent and PaRSEC. The benchmark results show that TaskFlow generally achieves the best performance under various circumstances.

Asynchronous RPC Library (ARL)

LBNL

Advised by Prof. Aydın Buluç and Katherine Yelick

Aug. 2019 - Jul. 2020

- o Data-driven HPC applications suffer significant overheads for their fine-grained communication patterns. ARL is a thread-based RPC system that targets data-driven applications. It uses Remote Procedure Call (RPC) to provide powerful expressive ability. It achieves high performance through node-level aggregation, single-node work-stealing, and innovative concurrent data structures. It also provides a flexible programming interface for users.
- o Node-level aggregation is the primary idea underlying the ARL, which aggregates RPC requests sharing the same source and target node and sends them together as one large message. Using this methodology, ARL is able to utilize high bandwidth across cores on the same node to achieve low overhead and high throughput.
- o I am the main developer of the ARL. ARL is developed as a C++ header-only library based on the GASNet_EX communication library.

Patent

o **Jiakun Yan**, Jingzhu Shao, Zhen Huang, Yanzhou Xiang, Yutong Liao, Ruohan Hu, Jin Qi, Shuo Jiang, "A vibrating alarm clock based on pressure sensors", Utility model ZL 2017 2 1300094.X, China

Honors and Awards

- o Chinese University Student Computer Application Ability Competition, the first price. 2019
- o **Fan Hsu-chi Scholarship** Awarded to about 10 top students in SJTU every year. 2018-2019
- National Scholarship Highest honor for undergraduates in China, awarded to top 0.2% students.
 2017
- o Zhiyuan Honorary Scholarship Elite program scholarship for top 5% talented students. 2016-2019

Skills

- o **Programming Language:** C (proficient), C++, Python, Java, Rust, Go
- o **Library & Framework:** libibverbs, libfabric, MPI, Argobots, CUDA, GASNet-EX, UPC++, OpenSH-MEM, Pytorch, Android, Qt